[SPEAKER_01]: What is permanence?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arising is manif... Well, in the sūtra, it says, arising is manifested, ceasing is manifested, persisting or changing is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I don't want to repeat myself, but basically, impermanence pertains to that manifested bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it won't be found in actual arising, or ceasing, or persisting, or changing, because those things are all phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: And impermanence pertains to the nature of the phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Persisting while changing as a phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you... Well, arising is already persisting or changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see the actual origin of the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point, I mean the exact split second.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you just have a thing arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, whether it's arising or whether it's ceasing, it's like fading in and fading out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And fading in, it's only a form of endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same thing that it's increasing in its presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's persisting as the same thing while it's changing, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: increasing in its presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same goes for fading out, for decreasing in its presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, whether you're witnessing with your senses, arising of some, like, manifestation of a thing, like, poof, something just appeared, or poof, something just disappeared, both of those things arise for you in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Assume when you are looking at the actual disappearance of something, that is appearing for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the disappearance in a particular level, external level, but as an experience, it's actually arising, it's appearing for you, it's manifesting for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's that confusion, because we spoke before, between the usages of arising and arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you should really distinguish between arising, ceasing, persisting or changing, and what manifesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because arising is manifested, ceasing is manifested, persisting or changing is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from that point of view, you could say arising arises, ceasing arises, persisting or changing arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, it appears.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're saying it's always... it is always... Impermanence pertains to that manifestation, to that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't pertain to you having to witness a destruction or disappearance of a thing in order for you to know the impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even the Sotāpanna's insight says whatever has the nature of arising,
[SPEAKER_01]: has the nature of ceasing and knowing the nature means actually that thing is still in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, far from seeing it being destroyed in order to realize the impermanence, you actually need it to be arisen in order to see it as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why people have a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: People who
[SPEAKER_01]: Think the practice is like denying nothing's real, nothing exists, see, the science is sure, this is always changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They basically never allow things to manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, I mean, you can't really stop them from manifesting, but they never discern the fact that things manifest because they're too busy denying them.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of that, well, they just completely cover up any possibility of understanding what the real impermanence is, the impermanence that matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: The impermanence which, if you were to understand, frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what about impermanence?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, things... a thing is arisen, always.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always this thing arisen, like the five yogis are.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's always a thing manifested, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Manifested experience is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that general experience...
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing that is unmanifested is nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is un...?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The unborn, the... that's... that's something.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ultimate, like, negative of your experience is there, but it doesn't manifest in a sense that everything else manifests.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's like a negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, for abandoning everything else, you develop nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't just go into nibbāna, because there will be another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But on that most general level of experience, the thing...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for as long as you have the five aggregates, there's always something manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, Buddha Vipassi, before he became the Buddha, he was contemplating arising and falling, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: manifestations of any kind, of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, on the most general level, he was contemplating the nature of arising, means nature ceasing, because it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he became the Buddha, just through that contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, exactly, whether you
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless your aggregates break apart, any experience that you witness, that you go through, that you experience, even if it's a destruction of every single thing in the world, even if it's a destruction of your own senses, that arises for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That disappearance appears for you as disappearance of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because things arise, or rather, everything is discerned and arises on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when the mind comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I have to understand impermanence?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in order to understand impermanence, you have to discern the arising of things, their manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to discern the nature of their manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you see that they manifest, and you have absolutely... it's inconceivable for you to have any say in their manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just like you're completely
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in... it's inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot possibly even conceive it in the utmost obstruction, how it would be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... the mind cannot go there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that, you know, for this very reason, that I have no say in their manifestation, that's why things are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why things are distanced from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they cannot be myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that you need to figure out, then, what not-self means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, by seeing the impermanence correctly for what it is, that's automatically the experience of not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's a different thing, but it's basically the same spirit that consists of different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're saying it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's... yeah, it's within... it's within the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: Always, like, when people, when you read the suttas or any contemporary Buddhist, whatever, interpretations, you just assume, oh, impermanence, impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must see arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, and then you look for the impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why lots of people really commit to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You end up experiencing frustration.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I know I'm speaking from experience, because no matter how much, like, you know, you might even destroy things that mean to you, just to show.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, that's another arising of another experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the experience that is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Nicha means, not the actual things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as the... one of the wrong views of the... of the Western science, and I remember we studied it from chemistry, like, nothing can get destroyed, it's only the energy and the molecules which change the shape.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the... the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I forgot the name, so I don't wanna...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't wanna get it wrong, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: It was the name of a law, inverted commas,
[SPEAKER_01]: Which was basically like when you burn... say you burn a piece of wood, well, that energy, that object, it's just changed its form now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now it's smoke and now it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's transmuted into... Well, it's basically like it's impossible to destroy the matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, like, from a completely wrong view, they kind of arrived
[SPEAKER_01]: At the outside of what I'm talking about, when you realize... Because, basically, matter or non-matter, the only way you can know matter is through your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, obviously, scientists, they deny the validity of personal experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: They generally project it outside as it's a matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a genuine matter that they are accessing and dealing with, not their experience of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, they say, oh, it's a genuine matter that you cannot destroy.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, basically, what they're saying is, even the destruction is another experience for you, so you can't destroy your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Buddha goes even further, saying, even death would not be a destruction of your experience, because you continue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only Arahant truly destroys the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: By abandoning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By seeing that he could have not have... that he could have not have owned it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He could have not had owned it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, well, one or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: He could have...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's... he could have not owned it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's the best one.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter what.
[SPEAKER_01]: And fully understanding that, he just, like, he has... he automatically lets go.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I need to let it go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Automatically, it's abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean, like, you discern, oh, it's arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, sorry, through manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through something that is present, you go, it's arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's increasing that very manifestation that's already manifested, or it's decreasing that very manifestation that's already manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just both.
[SPEAKER_01]: The manifestation is enduring still of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't, like, concern yourself with moments of its arising, moments of its persisting, moments of its cessation, because it's a completely wrong view and you can't even see those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all you're seeing is your own experience of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that experience is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you assuming yourself as, like, external to it, and then observing of its linear progression, linear kind of endurance in time, whereby a thing arises, oh, it's still there, and now it's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, see, you left yourself completely out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you also fail to see that even now, the experience of now this thing is gone, that is present for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But your mind is out concerned with that external object of your senses, and you genuinely believe that now it's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, it's not gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as you've been thinking about it and exist in your, like, well, even for as long as your five aggregates exist with this intact memory in the mind, that thing has its form of, has a form of its presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you can't find its material counterpart anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or other material aspects.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not exactly a counterpart.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is how you can still think about people.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're died.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or they're gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that have been destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: They haven't.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a phenomenon, those things are still manifesting in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the external projection of the matter and stuff, whatever else wrong views people might have,
[SPEAKER_01]: Where you think the world exists independent of you, or you exist independent of the world, or both, or neither, or you're confused in regard to it, then, yeah, you will believe that this material aspect is the thing, but then, see, then you can't account for your thinking of it when that matter disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing was never in the matter, nor was never in your mind, in your consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing was always comprised of both.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, it's that very absence of that matter that stands for the matter of that thing when you think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: A negative matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah!
[SPEAKER_01]: This, my favorite thing, is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: It used to be right here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, the empty space becomes the material aspect of the matter you're thinking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it was always name and matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the views that people have, projects, gives the priority to the matter, which is why you keep looking for the distraction of the matter, to find the proof for impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no external proof for impermanence, because that's another thing that arises, and another thing that you can take to be permanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the proof for impermanence is in arising of things, or rather, the... the proof for things
[SPEAKER_01]: Things impermanence in its nature would be in the nature of that thing's manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, things are impermanent not because you can observe their destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things are impermanent because they have arisen in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's beyond your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can still conceive a form of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say, ah, this is beyond my control.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can see a sense of control in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you really drill this deep enough, it becomes inconceivable, even in that remote sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all you're going to find is a reason... is things manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, through that manifestation, you can discern how it's arising, how it's ceasing, how it's persisting, while changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's manifesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the bottom line.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's right there, where you can see, because it's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even the word manifests.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, something's shown to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, nothing to do with you, just... it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh!
[SPEAKER_01]: For that very reason, it won't be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you can destroy, not because others... not because... no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply because it came uninvited.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's birth.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole existence, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the nature of the five aggregates, to arise and fall.
[SPEAKER_00]: To be manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: To be manifested to you, on and on and on, until they break apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, in regard to the five aggregates, you establish that assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: That they are yours, that you are theirs, that whatever, that you're in control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, that's how upādāna gets involved with... in regard to the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't really... Like, the five aggregates are not upādāna, but there's no upādāna without the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the Chula Veda, I think.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point is, they are indifferent to you, the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: They go their own course.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the interference due to the ignorance, not knowing that you cannot interfere.
[SPEAKER_01]: That lack of knowledge is the form of interference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that interference, in regard to them, can't really change the five aggregates or do anything with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can certainly feel the assumption that you are, that you are in control, that they're yours, that they belong to you, that whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But all they do is manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because they manifest, they cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in terms of... Well, maybe we can go to that sutta, 35, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_00]: Madhyamikāya.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's 35.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one with... Do you see this?
[SPEAKER_00]: 39.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's sort of with the... when that person assumes that consciousness gets reborn, but consciousness passes on from life to life to life, and he says that's what the Buddha taught.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, this is about the Venerable Asaji.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, do you find him?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, I think, yeah, I think, but it's it's right after something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do remember that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thirty-eight.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, do you see?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because this has come to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's thirty-eight.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, eh, it's, eh, mahātana, sankhāra, sūta.
[SPEAKER_01]: The greater discourse on the disruption of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sat, bhikkhu sati.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the sound of the, it's the sound of the fisherman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sound of the fisherman.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's... what started with... he has a view that consciousness gets reborn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he thinks it's the same consciousness that runs among us through the realms of rebirths, not another.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, in experience, things just are.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, too soon it's... you've...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the only way you can think is to assume it, because it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable to, like, you can't even conceive, like, the rebirth, in the sense of something would be...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your ideas or assumptions that come as a result of, like, ignorant manifestations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, things are manifesting to your five aggregates throughout your life, and you have ignorance in regard to that, and you base these external assumptions
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you think, ah, it must be this that's passing to the next life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But everything, even this, even the idea of this, and the idea of the next life, and the idea of passing, all of that is already fully affected with those wrong assumptions that you have in regard to your own, like, fundamentals of your own experience from the very start.
[SPEAKER_00]: But his view is almost like this passing point between this life and the next life, that doesn't exist, but there's
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all the passing from this consciousness to that, which is a thing in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a thing in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, we say that the limbo is another realm, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: If someone, you know, if he passed from this life into limbo... Yeah, well, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...between lives, well, that is a life.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another life, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's always...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the manifestation of the ego is continuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: But where he is... And you can discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how many lifetimes somebody can remember, whether it's one, five, five hundred, five
[SPEAKER_01]: All they're going to remember is the arising and passing of the manifestations of the five aggregates of one particular among them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they won't... they can't imagine the in-between.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because there is no in-between.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another thing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In-between exists only between the two things, and that in-between is the third thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in-between, as a negative of the both things, it's a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I meant, like, even the absence of a material
[SPEAKER_01]: Aspect of a certain thing that you're thinking of, that absence is a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why space is often listed as one of the... with great elements, with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have four great elements, earth, water, fire, air, space and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you look at it, there's a very little distinction between them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even space, the negative, the absence of matter, serves as matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the consciousness is listed within, because the consciousness is actually, in that sense, external, with that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't conceive... well, you can conceive, sorry, you can conceive matter, which is more for the understood, eh, but truly, you can't access the matter, but in the same sense, you can't access your own consciousness, because it's on your own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness is out there, with those four great elements, outside of your reach.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you're going to have,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically nāma-rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all that appears.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how remote, how ambiguous, how distant, how abstract, it's still within the nāma-rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have the experience of consciousness in itself, or matter in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you're going to have is conscious matter, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: the real experience of nāma-rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: But both ends of that experience, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: consciousness and the matter, are external to you, inconceivably inaccessible, which makes nāmarūpa inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can just be witnessing it, well, suffering on account of it, or whatever else, but you can't access it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: In its nature, it manifests, and for those reasons, it ceases.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just because it manifests, just because it comes from the direction that it's
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would be like you're wearing borrowed clothes, but you have no idea where it came from, and you have no idea when it's going to be taken away from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's everyone's life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Entirely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, well, like, you know, I can still enjoy borrowed stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could, if you were to know when the person's going to come and take it away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I still have two months to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can be after the next in-breath, and that that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be taken away from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you realize, oh, okay, I better adjust my plans accordingly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no people adjust their plans accordingly, or very few do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when things are taken away from you, they're always in the, like, in distress.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you... there's nothing based on...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't plan, like to simplify it a bit, if you don't plan anything on account of borrowed things, and those things are taken away, you will remain completely unaffected.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, when death comes, you will be completely unaffected if you don't plan anything on account of life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because life is a thing that... that's borrowed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, death can't be in front of you, and then you decided to borrow it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have no idea who owns it,
[SPEAKER_01]: And who'll take it away?
[SPEAKER_01]: At what time?
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha did say something similar.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, eh... Mara can do with people what he wants, because they come to his territory and use his things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like a bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, on account of that, he's in charge of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, what are those things?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you might think, oh, unwholesome behavior is those things, or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much more than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those things are your eyes, your ears, your nose, your tongue, your... your whole sense base.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's kind of like that whole modern surrealism.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so whatever appears, it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, funny enough, we're going to say, whatever appears, it's impermanent, because it appears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what appears?
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything that you know of, everything that you think of, everything that you might see or hear or think of, it will have that in common, that it will appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that reason, it will not be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, it cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you might take it, so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or he says, everything becomes like a piece of wood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or a stick goes... Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, when he asked the monks in the forest, like, would you, like, well, some of you would probably be... How do you say?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he was basically talking about the, you know, people being upset on account of sickness or death, something happening to your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, he asked monks, would you be upset if somebody comes in these woods now and starts collecting these dried up twigs and branches that fell off the trees?
[SPEAKER_01]: And they're like, no, we wouldn't, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing to do with us.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you should regard yourself and your own body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, literally, this has nothing to do with me, because it has nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that also requires giving up the pleasures that you gain through that body, which is why it's so intoxicating.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, there's another sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was about to say it, but there is another sutta that says it better.
[SPEAKER_01]: If this human realm will only be consisting of pain, people wouldn't need much for prompting to go for liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It consists of that pleasure as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why people get intoxicated and blinded in regard to that which is hurting them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just don't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're intoxicated with little pleasure you get from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But both are within the nature of the borrowed goods.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you have no permission to borrow,
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly have no control how long you can use it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, it's even worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you think you own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine your surprise, when Mahārāja does come and collect what's his.
[SPEAKER_01]: What always was his.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there's another... like all the other suttas who often talk about the puppet on the strings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all the things you borrow are basically the strings that Mahārāja uses then to pull you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you hold on to those strings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the puppet is going where the strings are yanking him.
[SPEAKER_00]: But also, even that self, even that person that holds on to other inner things, experience, or that self that is manifest, that must also be seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just see everything with the same right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even that sense of self, it's... it's a reason, it's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can designate, you can... it's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha never said there is no self.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, well, basically, there is not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that which you take to be yourself, that sense of self, doesn't belong to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like still being able to see wrong view, but with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have it... you have that wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that sense of self is actually
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as Indriya said, it can often be just a sense of an individual, a sense of a particularly unique set of five aggregates, that you take to be like the most personal aspect of your experience, so you take it to be yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no matter what sense of self it is, how strong it is, leave it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't try to deny it or negate it, because there will be again denying the things that you can't even deny.
[SPEAKER_01]: They manifest on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're trying to cover up the contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people end up being very frustrated.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, no, allow your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, see your sense of self as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, basically, it's other words saying, see your sense of self as manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: In very ambiguous terms, but it's still manifested as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then,
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't regard it as belonging to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because even yourself... it was... it's just... yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing in your experience you could have created.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can abandon everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of it can be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the idea that something can create things without being a thing itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you feel like, oh, you need to undo certain processes or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order for it to stop, and then you can really abandon self.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already the act of yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why at any time you can see the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter what situation, good or bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you look through the whole thing, including your sense of self, and not own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, recognize that you can't own even your sense of self, which is why it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is that which you take to be self, but it's not yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what that sutra is about, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: When it continues, it's about, do you see this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, it comes back to the very fundamental nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see this as manifested?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, Venerable Sir.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see it manifested with this as a condition?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see it with the disappearance of that condition?
[SPEAKER_01]: What has come, what is manifested, has come to cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like this, this remains standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to introduce that, like, a determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do see this as a condition of the manifested thing, while you're seeing the manifested thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not an explanation of a linear causality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this A creates B and I'm watching both, thus I'm not myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, and that's just complete magical thinking, where you project, okay, so what does that mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, all the things are impermanent and constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The scientists say the atoms and molecules are never in one, electrons are never in the same spot, da-da-da.
[SPEAKER_01]: So?
[SPEAKER_01]: I still suffer on account of unfulfilled desires, on account of being paired with people I don't want to be paired, being separated from people I don't want to be separated from.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter what scientific view I might do, it doesn't pertain to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you see it, all those things are manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say manifested by oneself, on their own, it means determined by something other than you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, the entire manifestation is completely out of your hands.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that's the direction where they came from, that determination, these fears, they cannot possibly stay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you're gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your experience is taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So he says, do you see it as determined by something else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, in this particular sutta, he uses the nutriment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you see its nutriment?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And its nutriment is something that you don't necessarily see particularly.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because that wouldn't be a nutriment, it would be another thing that's now nurtured by something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why I say, while you're aware of the manifested thing, within that manifested thing, you can discern its nutriment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not by
[SPEAKER_01]: Looking away from the manifested thing and then... Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then you will be looking at another manifested thing that you will think is the nutriment of the previous manifested thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see how you kind of squeezed yourself out and made this whole relationship external.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's external, it won't be the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Needs to arise internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, needs to arise within the manifested thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The nutriment would be then the real nutriment because you haven't abandoned the manifested thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can we talk about this?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not A and B.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's A and smaller A.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that A.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the general experience and particular things inside it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's a very general thing to put.
[SPEAKER_01]: To put it that way, it's just like... Too general?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you say it's just general and particular, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's too general as an explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... Well, again, general thing can become particular, if you forget about it as general, and then, you know, you rather experience it more generally in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you still think you think of general thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means whatever is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any of the aggregates, whatever is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can just go, as we spoke before, the presence of your body, the presence of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two simultaneous things, inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can see, when you think about the body, well, that's a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your own body...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everything shares the nature of a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what does that mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because everything manifests on the level of a mental image.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while you have the mental image of that certain thing, you discern its nutriment within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And discerning its nutriment means discerning it as coming from something other than your assumed sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you said, like, you need to see a thing, depending upon something else, that cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that thing that is yours will be disowned, because you realize, actually, I can't own this, because if that thing, that I cannot own, disappears, this thing will not standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, that thing belongs to the other, belongs to its nutriment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot belong to me, because I have no say in its appearance, I have no say in its disappearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this, yeah, this has appeared
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, because of which this has appeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like this experience, this mental experience, this experience of nāma, rūpa, its nutriments, its... Well, we can speak about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can say the experience of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: That I said, self is a manifested phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you confuse to... well, that you conceive to belong to you, but it's on the outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can take your sense of self, that ambiguous sense of self, and it's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to discern its manifestation, whether it's through increasing its presence, decreasing its presence, or simply persisting either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you become skilled in, like, discerning manifestation, picking up the signs of things, that's like picking up the signs of your mind, cittanimitta,
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, then, when you think about, okay, what is this thing inseparable from?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is a necessary condition?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is a nutriment?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is a basis for this sense of self to be here?
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you have to, like yoniso manasikāra, the root, the womb, attention, means exactly that, goes to the root of the present thing, not to the root of another thing, of another experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you need that proper attention to discern within the present manifestation, to discern its conditions, or formations, or determinations, or saṅkhara, whatever you want to translate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, without abandoning the manifested sense of self that you're mindful of, you need to discern within that, what is that sense of self inseparable from?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whatever you find would
[SPEAKER_01]: Will, most likely, be a determination of the thing, unless you over-intended, or rather over-attended, that manifestation in looking for its nutriment, and then found other things that then became manifestations, and they themselves have their own nutriments within themselves that you have not seen, because your attention hasn't been trained to look through things, through a reason phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I was talking about in the Appearance and Existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like turning a sleeve inside out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inside out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to go through it, pick up the other end, and then pull it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the suttas refer to it like, you know, cutting deep with the probe, with the knife, and then pulling this thing out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else stays the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just that one bit, that one misunderstanding at the very root, covers and sort of poisons everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, back on the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it inseparable from, while that sense of self is present?
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that sense of self discern, what is inseparable from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you have sense of self present, without being able to think?
[SPEAKER_01]: Without having any mental images whatsoever, would you be able to discern that ambiguous sense of self in me?
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, would you be able to think?
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is no living body that is still operating and paired with consciousness out there in the world, you wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, if that living body paired because you were able to think, you wouldn't be able to have the sense of self, so then there wouldn't be a sense of self in that sense that would belong to you, because if something would happen to that body, something would happen to that consciousness, if something to happen to that ability to think, that sense of self goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, you can see all that, like, on a board.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can write it down as a chart, and it will all make good sense, explanation, but it will not be open-eyed, and it will certainly not free you from suffering or bring you closer to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not seeing it in the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by the right order, I mean, you don't... you're seeing it linearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see one within the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not next to... or while.
[SPEAKER_01]: One, while the other is still present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're seeing it left and right, up or down, but you're not seeing it within that thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take the self, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the whole, the whole ābhidhāma and the commentary is... that's why the entire attitude, the entire way of looking is completely wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: You... all the stuff from the suttas are there, rich and littered, like packed,
[SPEAKER_01]: It lists and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's all linear.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all out there that you can observe.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why there's always a reason, the order of things the Buddha would do.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wouldn't just list things out to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: He would be like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you see this has come to be?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that you see that this has come to be, that sense of self I'm talking about right now, that it's manifested, that you see it for what it is, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see it inseparable from certain nutrients?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it would not be able to occur... it would not be able to even be conceived without those nutriments present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, Lord, we see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, would you see that with the cessation of those nutriments, this will not remain standing even for a split second, inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the two sticks holding each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: You move one, the other one goes down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, Lord, we see.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he refers to that because this view is the purified and bright view as it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, just that principle is the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the kind of generic term for the right view is like, ah, whatever has the nature of arising has the nature of ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever is manifested will have to cease, basically, because it's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he said, even that view, as pure, as bright, like, you abandon even that.
[SPEAKER_01]: By using that view, you abandon all the wrong views, and then you just let go even of that view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the dhamma is truly taught as the, like, as a simile of the raft, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to take the sense of self again, why does this manifest?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's almost like you keep this in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you look at the whole... the two sides at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then start distinguishing the sides as within that front you're keeping.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't explain.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not spatial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't pertain to space.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I know what you mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just saying...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's so easy to confuse what comes first, what comes second.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of the same, on the same level.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is first, there is second, depending on what you attend.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, you can over-attend and then start attending those supposed nutriments of your sense of self as separate senses of self, as separate things that you just took to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, you want to have that thing in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense of self
[SPEAKER_01]: Within this very present sense of self, you discern things without abandoning.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while you're mindful of the sense of self, within that mindfulness of the sense of self, you discern things that this sense of self isn't separable from, as sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: It probably isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, see, then we'll be overdoing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can call it later, five hundred years.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like, Nibiru said, ah, well, like, somebody might not necessarily use the twelve-factored explanation, but did some part, because all they see is, with this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with these nutriments, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you see it in reverse order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, later, you can start discerning more and more where you become proficient in that principle, as when there were non-believers who said, oh, this is so easy, you see it all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: People said, no, don't say that, because, like, for the very reason people don't see that, which you find easy now, they remain bound to saṃsara for, like, well, intolerable amounts of times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I mean, I can enable my sense of self now.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it with the sense of self?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is this nutriment?
[SPEAKER_01]: I can see... You can simplify it, but as long as you do it right, like according to... Well, as long as you do the principle right, you can simplify it as you want in terms of designation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can just say with this, this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in your mind, see thing within a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not thing next to the thing, not thing before the thing, not thing after the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thing within the present thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's akālika.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's timeless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does not pertain to time, because it's one within the other, simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I learned in the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember using saying, like, when it feels like a thought, a thought closes upon itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't go left, you don't go right, you don't go to another thought, you have a thought present, whatever shape or form, and within that, you sort of, well, let it go, in a sense, see it impossible to own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you have no, like, well, not as you have no idea where it came from, it's just the direction of its origin is just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you just have a thing that isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that very reason, you recognize a thing will cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, a thing is impermanent.